<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bike by bike</title>
    <description>A life, one bicycle at a time.
</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jun 2018 09:42:26 +1200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Jun 2018 09:42:26 +1200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>1. The Mustang</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I was seven, so I had suspicions about the factual status of Santa, but here she was wheeling something into the bedroom, backlight by the hall light. She did not have a beard. She looked a lot like my Auntie Sandy. So unless Auntie Sandy was keeping a secret, Santa was history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing she was wheeling made a soft ticking sound. She leant it against the wall and closed the door, taking the light with her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Santa was lying face-up on an icy slab, a paper ticket wrapped around his toe. ‘Deceased’. And did I care?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not. This was much more important, this was My First Bike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter how excited I was I knew I couldn’t get up and ride it immediately. Technically it was past midnight so it was the 25th of December but I knew that was the kind of perfect reasoning that adults failed to appreciate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t know what kind of bike it was, what colour it was, what it looked like. And these things were very important. I spent a long time gazing at the few faint glints of chrome that I could make out in the dim light, trying to will it into a solid presence, but it remained an idea of a bicycle, a friendly ghost that made it into my dreams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the morning there it was, across from me, in clear, glowing colour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bright yellow. Loads’a chrome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wake up boy - come out and ride!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I close my eyes I can remember the bike standing bright against the black and red chessboard of the chenille bedspread on the spare bed, the ticking of the house as the wood warmed and expanded in the sun, and that peculiar stillness that surrounded my Grandparent’s house, as if time had stopped some years ago and was gazing fondly back on the nineteen sixties. My grandparents, June and Tom, lived in a house at the end of a dead end street on the outskirts of a small town in New Zealand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/1-tams.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Taumaranui High Street. This photo somehow makes it look busy.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re a New Zealander you might know Taumarunui. Back in the day it was ambitious enough to have a museum, and was useful enough to have one of everything – a hospital, a police station, a rotary, a masonic lodge, an amateur theatre, a golf club, a high school, a real estate agents (Grandad) a haberdashery (Grandma). And on that bright and clear christmas morning it had one very happy boy in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A bike, brilliant!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;callout-right&quot;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt; Xmas down under&lt;/h4&gt;

I should note that we are taking about the southern hemisphere here, and that Christmas is a time of sunshine.  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

The days were scorching hot. The grass would make your skin prickly with heat, the adults couldn’t do much beyond slouch in easy chairs following a traditional Christmas meal – lamb roast, maybe a turkey, plum pudding – all taken in twenty five degree heat.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was called a Mustang. A bike named after a horse. A wild American horse. And the added tang of the Mustang muscle car. It had a touch of both. Bright yellow with everything chromed. A single coaster brake, and a banana seat. The stickers were small pictures of a cowboy rounding up a horse with a lasso. I guess that was meant to be me, the free spirited cowboy taming the wild beast and submitting it to my will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was only one problem - I didn’t know how to ride a bike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I told my son this recently and he was amazed. “You didn’t know how to ride a bike – at seven!?” Like most bike-mad parents I inflicted a strida-bike on him at 18 months old and he was riding comfortably at three. He was on his third bike by the time he was seven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/1-lawn.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Learning to ride.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So christmas day was spent learning how to ride a bike on the back lawn. It was sunny and warm. There were lots of family there and I remember my cousin Sonya feeding a lamb. A lamb that became a sheep that, a good few years later, I would watch my grandad gut. That I remember well too, the blood draining from the neck and the sudden spill of steaming intestines slopping down into the wheel barrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s like that, the country. Things can be cute, but they also had to grow up and be useful. There’s little room for beauty for it’s own sake, everything had to have a degree of the great kiwi virtue - &lt;em&gt;utility&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people at the time thought of bikes as a way of learning how to be on the road so that you could be a better driver later on. There was certainly no one I knew who rode a bike &lt;em&gt;as an adult&lt;/em&gt;. Such a thing would have been ridiculous. No adults I knew owned a bike. This was pre-oil crisis seventies, there was simply no need to own a bicycle. More than that, bicycles were reminders of WWII and rationing, and before that the depression. Bicycles were something you had if you were deprived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t feel any of that. I was having too much scary fun. From tumbling onto the grass I quickly graduated to the concrete drive and the next day onto the road. I was allowed to ride up to the end of the road, which terminated in a farm gate, and back to the house, perhaps fifty yards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a few good ‘look at me, look at me!’ ride-bys I was allowed to ride out of sight, right to the end of Rangaroa Road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/1-rangaroa.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Rangaroa Road and my Grandparents' house to the right.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was here that I discovered two of the abiding joys of cycling: 1) going down a slope, and 2) riding up the other side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was the smallest of dips, maybe five seconds of freewheeling and picking up speed before scraping the bottom of the parabola and having to really press the pedals to get up the other.  I repeated it, endlessly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The layout of The Mustang and its single gear made going up hill pretty much impossible. You sat a long way back on that banana seat, the handlebars’ backwards sweep pushing your hips a long way behind the axle. There was no way to get your weight forward on the bike other than awkwardly standing up and putting up with the handlebars bashing into your thighs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wasn’t concerned with such things at the time. The next few days I was off riding around Taumaranui, out of sight of the adults. A real taste of freedom and adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a parent now I know the simultaneous relief of having found something that a boy can wear themselves out on and the minor terror of letting them out of the house by themselves. Living in London I would be insane to let a seven year old out on a bike without a helmet and roam the suburbs unsupervised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taumaranui was perfect for such things. At ten I learned to ride a trail bike on my auntie’s farm, up and down the lumpy back blocks around Ongarue. When I was thirteen, Grandad gave me my first taste of driving, taking me out in his Austin Marina on the grassy Tuhua Domain, bumping around amongst the grazing sheep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My family was saturated with moving machines. My cousin turned out to be a national level enduro rider, various uncles looked after jets for Air NZ, my father raced cars for fun before giving it up shortly after meeting mum. These days everyone is still into their motors. Now members of the family restore vintage cars, ride 1200cc motorbikes, work as mechanics. One uncle once said that the only good horse was one with two wheels and a motor. No one laughed, this was a matter of fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt like I had been given a bike as a present and stolen unseen the real gift – the physical thrill of riding, the palpable sense of being unshackled. The bike was ‘mine’, but the &lt;em&gt;sensation of riding&lt;/em&gt; quickly became part of me and has never left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gleefully punting my new bike endlessly up and down the same piece of road, feeling the difference between smooth tarmac and chip, bumping onto pavements, repeating an arc again and again to explore inside the perfection of force that is a bicycle in motion. To be in the middle of this array of forces and to strive to understand them. That is what makes this Mustang my thing – not a horse, not a car – a bicycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cycling has a particular meaning for children. Aside from the sampling of freedom it has something to do with the very adult notion of having machines that amplify our actions. It’s the first taste of machines that take an intention and magically exaggerate it with levers and gears, tipping our desires out of the improbable and into the possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cars, boats, planes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What they say is &lt;em&gt;Look, I can run at sixty miles an hour, watch me as I, literally, fly&lt;/em&gt;. A child learning to ride a bike is getting an early taste of being allowed to self-power through life - to apply will to a machine and have it obey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if cycling is partly about finding the adult inside childhood the opposite is also true. Our bikes let us experience an innocent joy inside our adult life. The direct experience of force and motion is a rare thing for the modern city dweller. We are so often on other people’s timelines and  KPIs that it is a singular pleasure to propel yourself along the road, to use your own energy to get somewhere, in your own way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between the first turn of the pedals over forty years ago on a baking hot day in Taumaranui and the last one I took this morning on my way to work on a gloomy autumnal morning in London many things have changed. But the feelings have not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each time I set off on the stressful morning commute into the dark heart of London’s ancient, crumbling infrastructure accompanied by ignorant tin-tops and other, suicidally terrible, cyclists I wonder why I bother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A hundred yards down the road and I come back to the basics - this is me, sitting on 20lbs of metal, invoking the forces of physics to conjure delight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next: &lt;a href=&quot;/bikes/2-the-difficult-second-bike/&quot;&gt;The difficult 2nd bicycle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twitterati? &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/home?status=Bike by bike 1: First bike love @bikebybike&quot;&gt;Give us a tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2015 13:00:59 +1300</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/bikes/1-the-mustang/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/bikes/1-the-mustang/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>2. The Difficult Second Bicycle</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If the Mustang was the cowboy bike, something that wanted to be ridden across a flat plain in endless pursuit of the american cliche, my second bike was one that begged to be ridden to the village shop by the vicar’s wife.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About the same time I got this bike we moved house. From a two bed in Miramar to a three bed two-storey on the top of the bony ridge of Seatoun Heights Road. Moving up, in all ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t know it at the time but this was something of an attempt by my mother to save the marriage. To get something to change. Anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An age-old story this. A woman finds a man who seems sensible and stable but in the end doesn’t like the eventual lack of dynamism. And back then some men still thought that women should do all the housework, even if they both worked full time jobs. That’s a reduction of course, there was a lot more going on in there, but that’s the heart of it. Men who won’t change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let’s get back to the bicycles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the Mustang was lifted over a fence by some local crook never to be seen again - I cried, a lot - I needed something new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Truth was the Mustang was a terrible bike for the terrain we lived in. One back coaster brake and no gears in a place where the hills come at you short and steep. It was over-geared riding up the hills and a treacherous proposition coming down. While having no front brake reduces the chances of going over the bars in a panic stop it also increases the chances of you sailing across an intersection when the puny back brake fails to scrub enough speed off your descent. It was a good thing I lived in the burbs, and the volume of traffic was low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2-camperdown.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The local 'dare' hill, Camperdown Road, required a lot of nerve to ride down on a coaster brake...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bike came up in the local paper. Three speeds, 26inch wheels, two brakes. As new. Perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only problem was it was a ‘ladies frame’. I must have still been in that phase of boyhood before the hormones kicked in, where my parents rational arguments made sense. Their logic was that the ladies frame meant I had plenty of room to grow. And they were prepared to spend $100 on a bike, for me. That was quite a bit of cash back then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We bought it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2-a.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Looking a bit cross about new bike.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I started with the white plastic quilt-effect saddle at the lowest point in the seat tube, and most of my early riding was done in that hovering position that kids have on bikes which too big for them. The brakes were better, but in the rain the steel rims meant the thing had the stopping distance of an ocean liner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having three speeds was, however, a revelation on the hills. I can remember the first time I rode this thing up from the Miramar flats to the top Seatoun of Heights without getting off and pushing. A major achievement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;callout-right&quot;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Col de Newport Terrace (HC)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2-strava-awa.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had just hit puberty proper so was beginning to find my strength. Soon after that I was regularly riding it up all the hills, even Camperdown Road. I was the only one of my peers able to do this. Let’s face it, I was the only one of my peers who cared. Riding a bike up a hill without getting off became ‘my thing’. Maybe I was trying to make up for riding that horrible bike by showing that I was ‘the man’ regardless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About this time What Things Looked Like started to matter. No more hard black school shoes on the weekend - I wanted that latest innovation from England - TRAINERS. I wanted corduroy trousers with a bit of flair, not shorts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the bike that I wanted, that every boy on the planet wanted, was not a ladies bike in egg-shell blue with white handlebar grips and seat and a chromed mudguards and chain guard. Every boy in the universe wanted a Chopper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2-chop.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Cycling geeks note this is advertised as ‘a fully integrated design’.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike something contemporaneous like the movie Star Wars which is still a decent film, the Chopper was a complete triumph of marketing over good sense or practicality. Particularly in a town like Wellington.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wellington, on a good day, is unbeatable. Set on a natural harbour the sea is a beautiful deep blue green, the rugged coastline is a delight, a endless natural kaleidoscope of rock, flax and light. On a good day walking around the coastline is a joy - the sun beats down on you, a rare gentle breeze cools you and you can spend hours pottering in rock pools, or swimming off white sand beaches that, by international standards, are deserted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;callout-left wide&quot;&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/9p3o208id7o&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;allowfullscreen&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately good days are rare. Wellington is known as ‘the Windy City’. It has a radio station called ‘Radio Windy’.  Sitting on the turbulent Cook Strait there is nothing between it and the roiling mass of the Southern Ocean, and Antartica beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a southerly buster the storm comes straight up off the freezing ocean. You can see it coming towards the south coast, a think finger of black cloud erasing all colour before it. First the wind, then a few huge drops of rain splat down on the road like pigeon droppings. By this time you’d better be inside, if not you will be subject to rain that blows horizontally across the ground. It doesn’t fall so much as attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re not used to it it can be brutal. An umbrella in Wellington is the mark of a newbie. It will be discarded in a rubbish bin within a day, a broken mess of bent spindles and exhausted hinges. When the wind ran over 50 knots our whole wooden house would shake in the wind. The carpet in the lounge would lift, forced up by the wind pushing up under the house. Everything whistles. The sound of wind being sliced by powerlines and the swishing of trees being pushed around by the wind is just normal, common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best place to be is inside, listening to the wind howl around the corners of the house and rain scattering across the windward windows like shotgun blasts. The worst place to be is on a bicycle that puts you in a position where you function as a sail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this weather Wellington is no place for modes of transport with any affectations. Things were built to last. Cars and policemen were solid. Even now the best selling vehicle in NZ is a Totoya Van. Useful. Handy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, this was the seventies. An instability threatened the traditional ‘dresses vs suits’ gender gap. Men wore open collars and showed their chest-hair but also had head-hair in waves and wore tight trousers. Women wore trouser-suits and talked about this ‘new’ thing called feminism. Some mum’s worked. A few, like my Mum, worked full-time. The careful workers and savers of the sixties were being swallowed whole by a generation that wanted to change and to (gasp) enjoy themselves. We’re talking fondues and conversation pits and swimming pools and colour TVs. Dad’s had Pink Floyd. Mum’s had French cook books and Delia. Rich kids even had Lego. These things were not Useful or Handy - they were colourful and indulgent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;callout-right wide&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2-chopper-estate.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The boy version of wanting to a part of this was The Chopper.  Now that I live in the UK I can see the sense of it. Nothing better to ride the flat 300 yard triangle between shop, school and home, where most of what you would do with a bike was just sit sit on it drinking lemonade and encouraging your friends to go shoplifting. It was a posers bike, pure and simple. A Triumph Stag for ten year olds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And about as useful in the real world. The people I knew who had choppers spent all their time pushing them up hills and then riding back down in a state of giddy terror. That tiny front wheel, ape bars and all the weight on the back meant they were very light on the front - a touch of damp on the road and you’d lose the front wheel and get a whack on the chin from those ape bars. Death traps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite my parents progressive nature there was zero possibility of getting a Chopper. They thought it was dangerous. Whether that referred to its rideability or its cultural significance it is hard to say, but at the time I had about as much chance of a Chopper as getting a stereo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;wanted&lt;/em&gt; a bike that had aspirations and looked cool but was practically useless. I &lt;em&gt;owned&lt;/em&gt; a bike that was practical and better in so many ways. It actually went around corners. It stopped (as long as it wasn’t raining) and you could ride it up hill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I hated it with a passion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I did the only thing I could. I would force my parents to buy me something new by wrecking it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They didn’t notice what I was doing. They had other things on their mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The marriage started to simmer with toxicity in the radioactive prelude to the mutually assured destruction that would soon follow. It was all incomprehensible to me and, in reaction, I entered a dark period. Shoplifting, putting crackers in peoples letterboxes, stealing my parents cigarettes and coughing up stolen chocolate in dirty patches of trees. Not exactly the fledgling crimes of a serial killer, but worrying none the less.  I’m pretty sure my parents were more concerned with my behaviour and sanity than with the aesthetics of cycle choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, all too suddenly, being alone with Dad in the house, my parents separated, the custody swaps simmering with hatred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a familiar story that too many of my friends now are part of. The bloody he-said, she-said tallying of blame and fault. People trying to offset the intolerable pain with the impossible task of keeping everyone happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to watch. I listen to it all and sympathise but what I know as a child of (two) divorces myself is that divorce can be positive for the parents but it is a killer for the children. It’s a collision of confusion and illogical self-blame that kills your innocence and generates a dense strata of anger in your being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So yeah, I really felt like wrecking something. I stripped my bike of anything ‘girly’. Mudguards, chain guard, the white seat, the white handlebar grips all went in the bin. Lets be clear, it was still a ladies bike, but the significant hacks made it just about ridable in company. It was by no means cool, but it was ok.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My crew at the the time was a troublesome trio of myself, my English mate Neil and ‘Woody’ a fledgling heavy-metal drummer. Neil was the local cool kid, a year older than me. I got to hang around with him because I had the dual benefit of being both entertaining and easily led - an amusing victim in his schemes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neil had the defining good bike of the period, a Raleigh Twenty. These were about as cool as it got at the time, and when you stripped them they looked cool. They were good for wheelies and, without a front brake, you could spin the bars 360 degrees when riding slowly. He would let me ride his twenty sometimes - he never deigned to so much as touch my bike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three of us would take our bikes and ride loops around the neighbourhood, or play football (soccer) on the vast expanse of Miramar Park. We’d kill time building small jumps out of scrap plywood and bricks, find drop-offs and practice wheelies. I remember taking a brush and some red enamel paint from the house and slowly painting the name of our gang ‘Hazard’ on the broken tarmac of a piece of junk space. Tagging. Oh yes, we were cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Woody introduced me to Pink Floyd, Neil to his father’s pornography, but soon they were gone to the local boy’s secondary school, leaving me behind in Intermediate. No doubt much to my parents relief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2-b.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Round and around and around the house...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I calmed down a bit without Neil and Woody pulling me off the straight and narrow. The dust of the divorce had settled and, after a bruising period of manipulation and bullying, somehow my Stepfather ended up with custody, my Mother moving a couple of miles down the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there I was, back by myself, riding round and round the house. I spent hundreds and hundreds of hours on this bike, making up little obstacle courses and endlessly repeating them, trying to make less mistakes each time and not put my foot down. I would practise hovering the bike, stationary, counting out my previous record. Unconsciously exerting control where I was able.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did I mention I am an only child?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a difficult couple of years, and the hated ladies bikes had made it through with me. I might have loathed it but the three speeds still worked despite everything I could throw at it, the wheels remained round and true. Endless wheelies had finally exposed the weakness of the ladies frame structure and the frame had bent on the seat tube, a structural collapse from which there was no way back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had finally achieved my aim of destroying it. It was, undeniably, time for a new bike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next: &lt;a href=&quot;/bikes/3-america-calling&quot;&gt;America calling&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twitterati? &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/home?status=Bike by bike 2: Wrecking bikes and lives @bikebybike&quot;&gt;Give us a tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2015 13:00:58 +1300</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/bikes/2-the-difficult-second-bike/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/bikes/2-the-difficult-second-bike/</guid>
        
        <category>bike</category>
        
        
        <category>bikes</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>3. America calling</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This time I was determined to get a bike I wanted. And it was not going to be a Chopper. Choppers were &lt;em&gt;kid’s bikes&lt;/em&gt;. I wanted something that was properly cool, something that promised something new and exciting. I had to stop looking to England, at Raleighs, and start to look in a completely different direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Mum had been to America on a Rotary exchange in the 60s but she was unusual. Most Kiwis hadn’t travelled at all. We were  still a nation of flightless birds - it was three hours on a plane and a months salary to get to Australia. Air NZ didn’t even fly to London until the eighties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But TV programmes had started to make their way to NZ. There was nothing like the tsunami of content that the internet age bought with it, but in the 70s TV made a common appearance in the home. All one channel of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember getting the TV. I was five and the first programme I saw was something about American Baseball. As a kid I had no conception at all that there was a difference between English culture (Rainbow and Basil Brush and The Two Ronnies) and American culture (Batman and The Six Million Dollar Man and Fantasy Island) and that there might be something unique about Kiwi culture. We just watched everything - there was no choice - just that one channel. TVNZ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Cz2-ukrd2VQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/HoLs0V8T5AA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The Two Ronnies VS Six Million Dollar Man&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we lived inside a contradiction. Physically we lived in something drawn by very Kiwi concerns - farming and rugby sheep and Holden cars - but our televisual and reading experiences were from the two cultural powerhouses, the America and the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neither the country or myself could really decide which was better. Were we resolute Brit or Coolin’ in Cali? Was the country freewheeling and confident or stiff-upper-lip?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer for the country wasn’t clear at the time. In fact the future of NZ turned out be all about Maori and Pacific Island Culture and - for us whities - how it mixes in with the specific white NZ culture of the Pakeha. Apologies to my Kiwi friends who might find that last statement simplistic!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growing up in a postcolonial country identity isn’t something that you &lt;em&gt;find&lt;/em&gt;, it is something you &lt;em&gt;make for yourself&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The culture in which I was growing up was trying things out and discarding them as fast as I was - two pubescent brats riding a sea of hormones and changing who they thought they were day by day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You think I exaggerate? In the short length of my teenage years NZ went from a heavy-handed interventionist state run by a conservative government to a free-wheeling neoliberal economy run by a labour government. This was &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.naomiklein.org/shock-doctrine&quot;&gt;Naomi Klein’s Shock Doctrine&lt;/a&gt; in full flight, an extreme switch that made New Labour’s neoliberal reinvention in the UK fifteen years later look decidedly tame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I was was just a boy craving kicks, and, like many people in NZ, unconsciously I found the American Version of Life a lot more compelling. The UK gave us Blakes7, America gave us Starwars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4qklwSsBlbk?t=2m37s&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;On Any Sunday&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The movie ‘On Any Sunday’, partly backed by Steve McQueen, is an hour and half of people on motorbikes, but, at &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/4qklwSsBlbk?t=2m38s&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;2:27&lt;/a&gt; in there is 30 seconds of footage credited with starting the BMX revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Scooby Doo terms, it’s &lt;em&gt;those pesky kids.&lt;/em&gt; Californian kids took their Schwinn cruisers and ‘hacked’ them to ride on dirt tracks in emulation of their Motor Cross heroes and so invented BMX.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t see the movie, but I’d seen the bikes and it was an instant case of &lt;em&gt;WOW&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/3-spare.jpg&quot; /&gt;
Maybe it was the colours?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The colours you see around you in NZ, the quality of the light is much closer to the light in California than the light of Sheffield. Perhaps the posters of BMX appealed to me directly - here was a place that I could see myself. This wasn’t the muted brown world of Austin Marinas, the ochre yellows and deep reds of The Chopper. This was a bright world where people shone in the sharp, angled sunlight that burnt you to a crisp in under an hour. Yellows, purples and sky blues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever it was, BMX was The New Best Thing and I wanted to be part of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;callout-right wide&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/3-farm.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;NZ's first BMX track in '79 - basically a farm track&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a track that we went and visited, out on the coast, where lots of brightly clad boys in full face helmets fell off a lot and sometimes made it to the end. It looked scary, and fun - the two are closely related right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For BMX the affordable bike was the Healing HMX 500, a solid choice. The real racers choice was the Redline, a fully chromed masterpiece that hung like a jewel in the Burke’s window and cost over $300. I was so enamoured of this bike that would go to the shop out of hours and simply stare at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bike that sat in the middle of the affordable and desirable equation was _The Pantha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I was at intermediate school my world had grown beyond the Miramar peninsula and now included the Kilbirnie shopping area, home to ‘Burke’s Bikes’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/3-burkes2.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Burke's Cycles, where I bought bike number 3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent a lot of time lurking there, and it’s from there that I bought my Pantha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was staggeringly expensive, I think it maybe as much as $180. Dad gave me most of it, but my parents were pushing the contribution line so I still had to save hard on the pocket money and do extra chores in order to join the next cycling revolution. When I had most of the money I pointed to the black and yellow one and put it on ‘lay-by’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was in that shop all the time, looking at my bike. I was in there enough that one of the mechanics there, known as ‘Mouse’, recognised how hopelessly besotted I was. He was to prove a key enabler in my bicycle habit, but for the time being he just patiently led me through to the back room where my bike was propped up against some boxes, waiting for me to claim it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/3-packshot2.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Not a photo of my actual bike, but an exact likeness.&lt;br /&gt;
From: &lt;a href=&quot;http://bmxmuseum.com/bikes/pantha/49961&quot;&gt;BMXmuseum.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pantha had mag wheels, and a high bling factor. The black frame was offset by either red or gold highlights. It even had matching coloured tyres. Sitting on the showroom floor it looked like it wanted to go fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What escaped me at the time - and maybe I knew but I certainly didn’t care - was that Pantha was an NZ company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importing from the US pretty much doubled the cost of anything, so what started as a cheap sport over there became expensive by default in NZ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;callout-right wide&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/3-charles.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Cultural mix up&lt;/b&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Charles rides a NZ produced bike modelled off an American style in an English tailored suit...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s no accident that NZ is really good at things like manufacturing one-off luxury yachts. Before the days of cheap mass imports things in general were scarce and expensive. NZ was a kind of south-seas Cuba where people would make things from nothing much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Dad’s father Roy had what amounted to a full workshop under the house. My dad used to rebuild engines down there it was that well equipped. I am pretty sure, had he not died when I was 10, Roy could have made me a bike to order. He was not uncommon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So NZ was full of enterprises born out of basements and garages and sheds, some of them even hung on to become real businesses. &lt;a href=&quot;http://bmxmuseum.com/bikes/pantha/&quot;&gt;Pantha was not one of them&lt;/a&gt; but they were clearly an innovative and passion-led business that suffered from scale issues. Pantha was what we would call a start-up, some inspired guy going ‘I can do that’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally the day came where I had the last $10 and I was able to ride it out of the shop on my Pantha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boy did I feel good on this thing. Black! Gold!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, a cool bike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZX0qF1YHQ4U&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Nicole Kidman in 'BMX bandits'. It's not a Pantha she is riding, but it looks the same. &lt;br /&gt;And any excuse to watch something this bad right?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I started to ride it, however, I realised a few things. The alloy mag wheels may have looked cool on the shop floor but they weighed as much as the wheels off a stage-coach. The frame, likewise, must have been made of lead. It was heavier, and harder to ride, than my old ladies bike. It felt like I was riding underwater.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of that it only had one gear and I could barely ride it up the hills I had taken for granted on the ladies bike. The brakes were as effective as pressing bars of soap to the rims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be fair the Pantha was probably a good bike on the BMX track.  BMX races start at the top of a steep ramp and you get a hefty gravity-assist start. And no one really used the brakes during a race, they were more or less for show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there was nowhere around I could ‘do BMX’. There were some local trails in the Miramar hills that, many years later, provided some excellent mountain biking, but they were well out of the league of a bike designed for smoothed dirt berms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all the anticipation of owning this thing I was struggling with the realisation that it was much worse than my previous bike for just getting around on and no better for doing my laps of the house. The low seat meant it was exhausting to ride more than a couple of hundred yards at a time. The only thing it was better for was ‘drop offs’, where you ride over the lip of steep bank, keeping your front wheel in the air and trying to land the bike on two wheels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That aside, it was a dismal experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully it was also a brief. I realised that, as I had paid for a substantial proportion of this bike, that I was ok to maybe sell it and buy something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what to buy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was my first - and by no means last - awful bike choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had taken an expensive gamble and had chosen a bike based on what I thought it would let me do rather than chosen a bike based on what the riding I was actually doing. That’s called &lt;em&gt;aspiration&lt;/em&gt;. Not a bad thing at all, but in this case I fell flat on my face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was it Mouse who brokered the next deal? I can’t remember if it was him or whether it was a friend of a friend, but a couple of months after buying the Pantha I found myself swapping it for something very different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My next choice was nothing to do with aspiration, it just kind of happened. But in this case I landed the right way up. More than that - I landed the right way up and then vaulted to the heavens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next: &lt;a href=&quot;/bikes/04-ten-speeds-and-true/&quot;&gt;Ten speeds and true&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2015 13:00:57 +1300</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/bikes/3-america-calling/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/bikes/3-america-calling/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>4. Ten speeds and true</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I was an instant convert. I didn’t even look back at The Pantha. BMX? For babies. I had A New Thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually a very secondhand thing. A dark blue Raleigh. Ten speeds. Steel cottered crankset, gear changers on the downtube, heavy wheels. Ten speeds. Steel drop handlebars, corroded allow stem, steel seat pillar and a battered old Brooks saddle. And ten speeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/4-racer-full.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Back in the days when Mum's still cut your hair.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t look at the clothes, look at the cogs. Did I mention it had ten speeds? I must have seen ten speed bikes in Burkes, but I didn’t know anyone who had such a thing. What on earth would you need ten speeds for anyway?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back it’s easy to see this bike a beast. To start with, it was bent. Someone had pranged it and the down tube had a definite kink right up where it joined the head tube. The paint was chipped and fading, all the parts were heavy. Not Raleigh’s finest, something built to a budget. An abused example of the starter road bike of it’s day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was diddled on the swap. The Pantha was worth a lot more - it wasn’t beaten up and old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But those ten speeds. Revelation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You went as fast as you could, then you changed up another gear and you kept pushing faster and faster until either the road ran out or your heart was leaping out your nostrils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wasn’t about picking your way round obstacles of doing wheelies, this was about speed and effort combined. My effort made it fast. No limits other than what I could bring to it. Physically it demanded everything you had. I was soon a sweat-drenched addict, craving another burst, sucking up huge lungfuls of air and willing my screaming legs to turn one more time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was totally hooked on the sensation of it, not only going the exertion of going fast but tucking your head down and suddenly accelerating down hill, then leaning deep into a corner, going around it much faster than a car ever could; of sprinting all-out purely for the fun of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I could climb hills again, longer hills, steeper hills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/4-awa.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Possibly my favourite corner in the world, a joy on all of my first ten bikes, but a fresh discovery on the ten-speed.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Miramar_Peninsula_aerial.jpg&quot;&gt;Wikimedia image&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only faster, but much much further. I had just started high school (year 8 for my UK peeps) and my mother was determined that I would not be going to my father’s Alma Mater, an all boys school called Rongatai College.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;callout-right wide&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/4-cane.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The school I escaped.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rongatai was the kind of place you got strapped for walking on the grass. Or not having your socks at the right height. The headmaster was a pervert. I mean that literally - he was resigned a few years later after running an videod experiment on how to best use the cane on ‘willing’ participants. Nice guy, fun school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Rongotai was the place that all the boys went to. It was the local clearing house for hundreds of white boys on their way to becoming middling clerks in the pubic service. Why would you send your kid anywhere else?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My mother, bless her progressive socks, wanted me to go to a ‘worse’ school, Wellington High School. ‘High’ as it was known was situated around the back of the National Museum, right next to the Basin Reserve Cricket Ground. It had ethnic minorities. It had a loose uniform code. It had a Maori headmaster (pretty rare back then) and it didn’t have the strap. It had girls too - woohoo! But more importantly it had a lot of clever kids with progressive or arty parents who thought that it was the right thing to do send their kids to an inclusive and socially tolerant school. I was the kind of bright boy who was going to University anyway, so it didn’t really matter so much where I went academically - I wasn’t going to be needing much help in the that department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My new gang had parents who were doctors, accountants, teachers, journalists, artists and even, gasp, public intellectuals and lecturers. Peter’s dad was a philosophy lecturer and owned an ARP synthesiser. So now instead of figuring out how to avoid mirrors while shoplifting with my ‘friends’ I was figuring out which bits of wire to put where to get a sound out of this massive electric box.  It took about an hour to get anything of the ARP, but when you did it felt like the world had changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I went to my friends houses I had conversations around the dinner table and it seemed that some of the parents had minds subtle enough that they could argue from just about any point of view, just for fun.  Coming from Miramar (a long way from the film-centred progressive hub it is today) this kind of company was unexpected and very welcome. I started to live in the central city and spend as little time in Miramar as I could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/4-miramar.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;I'd spent pretty much all my life on the Miramar Peninsula before I went to High School. My ten-speed widened my horizons consderably.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Home for me was going home to my father, buying a takeaway and eating it watching TV. The house was a kind of vacuum, any feeling had been sucked out of it by the negative storm of the divorce. It’s not that there wasn’t love there, I know my dad loved me, but he was of the generation and personality type to not really know what to do with it.  Dad would come home with the takeaway, or maybe do meat and two veg, then he would play the piano for an hour or two. He would  then fall asleep in front of the gas heater, the only warm part of the house in cold weather.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The piano was  his sole emotional outlet - he is a gifted amateur musician - and I have a whole sub-strata in my subconscious of easy listening tunes and Jazz classics, all of them compressed and distorted from the weight of my father’s sadness and repression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;callout-right wide&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/4-lance.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Lance, another busted home kid. He did a little better than me on the bike, but a lot worse on the decent human being front.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the most part I would go to my room and read. I joke now that I was raised by wolves but I was living in a state of minor neglect. The house was never full of voices, never had parties, seldom laughter. It had two boys in it, one substantially older than the other, both trying to understand what was hell was going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is the ‘evil or absent stepfather’ theory of athletic achievement (see Lance Armstrong) and I would have to put up my hand here. Wanting to be away from home was, given the circumstances, understandable. ‘Proving myself’ is something that has never left me, though who it is I am trying to impress, and what will satisfy them, I have no idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are plenty of other adolescents with better family situations who ride bikes. Lets not forget just what a fantastic way cycling is to burn up all that energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/4-home-whs.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;My home to school segment.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would ride the 4.7 miles to school very quickly indeed, often less than 15 minutes (always less than 17), have my day at school, then do my paper round, then ride home, back up the hill. On arriving home I would put a pint of milk, a couple of tablespoons of sugar, a couple more of milo (powdered, sweetened chocolate) and then a scoop or two of ice cream into a big jar and shake it into a milkshake. After downing that I would put on my cycling clothes and go out ‘training’ for an hour or two, finishing with the ride up the hill again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bike also enabled me to ride all over town and visit my friends. I got to know the previously strange areas of Kelburn and Te Aro and Karori. Some of my friends parents even lived in Aro Valley, the actual inner city. So I rode that bike around the city a lot, and learned all the pleasures of the classic inner city climbs like Raroa Road and Devon Street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other thing I did was get a job, a paper round, and this minimal but independent wealth meant I could fantasise about a better bike. I had no idea what that meant, but occasionally I would see a real racer out on the road and feel an unmistakable urge to join their world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They wore strange, colourful clothes with French and Italian brand names on them and wore odd shoes. They had brightly coloured bikes with exotic names and really skinny tires. And they were fast fast fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/4-sumich.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;What racers looked like at the time. Roger Sumich laying it down right outside the KFC where my father would often buy me 'dinner'.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://oli-roadworks.blogspot.co.uk/2010/10/more-from-archives.html&quot;&gt;Off Oli's blog.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would still go in to Burkes once a week and talk to Mouse and talk about bikes. So it must have been in Burkes that I saw the poster about ‘Turn up and race’ for youth at the Haitaitai Velodrome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By this time I had bought some chamois shorts and my mum had made me a cycling shirt, so I didn’t look like too much of a dick when I showed up at the track, nervous, excited, looking at the other couple of dozen boys there and wondering where I stood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because it was a ‘turn up and race’ event we were all on road bikes. The Haitaiti velodrome is very long and relatively flat, so not very steep. It was also made of concrete so impervious to the kinds of damage our clunky old road bikes would inflict on a wooden track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/4-kids.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;PNP and Burke's still run 'starter' events, though they are more sophisticated - here's some really young kids on the same track.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a few laps to get used to it we all lined up and rolled over the starting line. I can’t remember how long the race was, probably only a few miles if that, but I do remember two things about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came third. And I loved it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was hooked. I thought about nothing else for the next couple of years. I became, pretty much over night, a racer boy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the two things a racer boys needs are a crew and a decent bike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next: &lt;a href=&quot;/bikes/the-wheels/&quot;&gt;Interlude 1 - The Wheels&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--
The drop bars help here. As any cyclist knows air resistance becomes the main thing that slows you down at anything over twelve miles per hour, so being able to put your head down  is the number one thing that will increase your speed - the less bulk you have in the wind the faster you can go. The other thing about 'assuming the position' is that the further forward you lean the more the butt muscles can do their thing. So 'position' is very important on a bike, as is 'the fit’ to achieve it.

//--&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2015 13:00:56 +1300</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/bikes/04-ten-speeds-and-true/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/bikes/04-ten-speeds-and-true/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Interlude - The Wheels</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Standing in the kitchen and begging my father for $100.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was not budging. His line was that this cycling thing would pass, like so many things pass in a teenager’s fancy, and he would be footing the bill for something that got abandoned and forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew he was wrong. I knew that this cycling thing wasn’t a fancy. Yes, it was a lot of money at the time, specially for something second-hand. But I knew that $100 was nothing to pay for a set of wings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I was pleading for were &lt;em&gt;The Wheels.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just before I got ‘The Gios’ I made a connection with a German Guy. He lived on the same street as Woody the drummer, so maybe he introduced me. Or it might have been the local paper. Remember those?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However it happened I found myself sitting in his house looking at a pair of wheels. All the wheels I had seen or ridden before had steel rims and big thick spokes - built to last, not built for fast. What the German Guy had in front of him was a pair or racing wheels. Campagnolo Hubs laced to Fiamme Red label tubular  (‘sew up’) rims. The spokes looked like piano wire they were so thin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/a1-title.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Campnogolo Record hubs - the first and only time I have owned a top-line piece of cycling kit.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I picked one up. I could scarcely believe it. My hand did that involuntary thing where it shot up because I was expecting something heavy. They seemed to be impossibly light, they must have been half the weight of the wheels on my Ten Speed - how could these things actually hold a person up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even by todays standards these things were light - a
Campagnolo Record back hub was around 250g and the rims 330g. So I’m guessing a built up wheelset minus tyres and cogs would be in the 1.5kg territory. That would cost around a thousand pounds in today’s money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only were they light they also spun forever. I am not one to drool over mechanical aesthetics but those hubs were smooth and very good looking. And they were made in Italy. In the real Europe. By Campagnolo. I am not going to do chapter and verse on ‘Campi’, but Tullio, the companies founder, was the one who invented the quick-release - something that hasn’t changed that much in nearing a hundred years. Campagnolo dominated the racing bicycle parts market for many decades, until the 80s when the Japanese started to want in on the act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;callout-right wide&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/a1-tubs.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Tubulars or 'sew ups' are much lighter and 'squishier' than ordinary tyres so ride faster and smoother - but you need special rims and they are expensive to maintain.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I told the German I didn’t have the money, couldn’t afford it. He wasn’t stupid, he understood. &lt;em&gt;But you have to try them&lt;/em&gt;, he said. He pumped up the tyres and we went out and dropped them onto my bike, he adjusted the brakes and let me loose on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Riding down Otaki Street they felt weird. Because they were so much lighter than my current wheels they had less centrifugal energy and so the bike felt tippy and odd. Not a great start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The magic happened when I turned around and rode back up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;callout-left wide&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/a1-mercury.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Mercury. Because this is important.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When people say that it doesn’t really matter what you ride I think back to those five minutes spent climbing back up to the German’s house. These wheels made a huge difference. It was like someone had given me an anti-gravity halo that bent the time-space contiuum and had me riding up the hill 50% faster for no extra effort. Or like Mercury, the winged messenger, was just behind me, pushing me up the hill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In cycling wheels matter. Two wheels turning and their accompanying gyroscopic force are the magic that make the whole thing work. And spokes - who thought of that? Who came up with this outrageous idea that 2kg of metal arranged in such a perfect way, can keep someone weighing 50 times as much off the ground at fifty miles an hour? It seems barely credible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond that minor miracle I have to say that which wheels you have matters too. An ordinary frame with extraordinary wheels is a much better bet than an extraordinary frame with ordinary wheels. People will spend £2000 on a bike with average wheels where they would be much better off buying a £1000 bike and spending the extra £1000 on some good wheels. But then image counts, and that £1000 bike with the good wheels doesn’t look as good as the £2000 bike, even though it will be quicker - people like to be seen to be &lt;em&gt;in the know&lt;/em&gt; with their… what shall we call them? Preferences? Brand values? Biases? Snobbery?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve been around bikes and cyclists a while you start to look at rider’s wheels, not their frames so much. A lot of riders will buy ‘factory’ wheels at various price points and some will spend the time to get wheels made for them, carefully selecting hubs and rims, going into detail about spoke counts and weights and rim widths, choosing a good builder and paying a little bit more for a custom set of hoops that suit their style of riding, their weight, their budget. Hand made wheels are the mark of someone who knows what they want to be doing, whether that it touring around the world or going as fast as possible for ten miles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After burning back up the hill I got back to the German’s house winded but wildly ecstatic. I wanted these things very very badly. Not only were they fast they made you want to go faster. Can you become addicted to pure sensation? Of course you can, and these were cycling crack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The German Wanted $100. That was $100 I didn’t have at the moment. That was many weeks of delivering papers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;callout-left right&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/a1-hubs.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;One last look at those hubs...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I went home to dad and begged. It was a lot of money for him too, not that he didn’t have money but he had a brutal financial plan - pay off the house as quickly as possible so that he could retire and go sailing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end he made some complicated arrangement with Mum that I was never party too. I didn’t know at the time that Mum was paying ‘maintenance’ and, despite her lower wage, she was effectively paying for the majority of my upbringing, so really he didn’t have much of a leg to stand on if Mum thought it was ok.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She must have thought it was ok.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got the wheels, and they formed the backbone of my racing cycling over the next couple of years. I had four different racing bikes through this period, and this set of wheels got popped into every one of them come race day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my father was wrong about cycling being a passing fad. To be fair he was right about tattoos and the future importance of computers, but &lt;em&gt;The Wheels&lt;/em&gt;, while they may be abandoned are never forgotten. Though I haven’t seen them since 1994 I still have them. They are hidden right down the back of my father’s attic - an act of Oedipal revenge?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will only have totemic value now as they have probably rotted and corroded to dust, but as far as &lt;em&gt;things&lt;/em&gt; go the only objects I have owned which have had a bigger impact on my life was my first computer, and, much much later, a maisonette in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next: &lt;a href=&quot;/bikes/5-gios-negra/&quot;&gt;Gios Negra&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2015 13:00:54 +1300</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/bikes/the-wheels/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/bikes/the-wheels/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>5. Gios Negra</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Mouse, bless him, did me the great honour of lending me a frame he had. It was way too small for him, but even so it was a very generous thing to do. At this distance in time I can’t even recall his real name - wherever you are Mouse, thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The frame, stove-pipe black, was stickered up as a ‘Gios Torino’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Real bikes from the factory of Gios Torino in the 80s were total works of art. Here’s one in full race mode under the gifted legs of Belgian hardman Roger De Vlaeminck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/5-hammer.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Roger De Vlaeminck doing the Belgain thing - hammering as hard as possible.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My bike, under the stickers, was actually a more mundane affair. My mate Oli who has ‘the eye’ reckoned it was a local hand-made frame made from Japanese, not Italian steel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t say I cared that much. It was a perfect size, was half the weight of the old Raleigh and was a big leap aesthetically - it &lt;em&gt;looked&lt;/em&gt; like an Italian frame and that would do me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;callout-right wide&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/5-gios-full.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;My bike looked a bit like this, but black.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people could afford to care, and in their eyes a locally welded bike made of Japanese tubing was not a proper bike. There was (and still is) lots of tosh talked about the difference between British Reynolds steel, Italian Columbus and Japanese Isiwata and Tange. All rubbish of course, a kind of snobbery that still has hold in some cycling circles where people are more concerned with the brand’s perceived advantage than it’s actual performance. The particular types of steel that are suitable for making bikes out of are all a lot more similar than they are different. There would be very few people who could tell the difference between identical frames made with similar grades of tubes from the various manufacturers. The geometry coupled with the diameter and thickness of the tubes has more bearing overall on how a bike rides than the grade of tubing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As in any small clique there’s a language of ownership in cycling where each brand has a specific place and makes a certain statement. Sometimes people spend a lot of money on bikes to show that they are serious. Sometimes people ride deliberately old bikes in order to show that have distain for people who spend a lot of money on bikes to show that they are serious. It’s all quite complicated and a good kind of anoracky fun. The irony is that anyone who doesn’t own a bike and speak this language simply sees ‘a bike’ and lumps the rider on a £8000 Colnago in with the rider on the £500 Halford’s special.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t pretend I didn’t want a beautiful Italian bike, but that was more about owning something that was exotic and ‘from the source’ than anything else. That and some of their paint schemes, which were amazing in that 80s ‘every neon colour possible’ way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Colnago Master is probably the highest form of the artful bike in the 80s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/5-master.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Some of the luxe paintwork on a modern Colnage Master.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my ‘Gios’ was a very average bike, by modern standards a bit of a lump. Back then  frames pretty much weighed the same and had more or less the same design. Sizing was simple. A 21” bike (my size then and for evermore) meant the seat tube and top tube were the same length, 21”. All bikes were like this, built ‘square’. If you wanted something with a longer top tube you had to take a longer seat tube.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;callout-left wide&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/5-roger.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;One last picture of Roger.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now I had the frame and The Wheels, so it was really only bits and pieces I needed. While parts from Campagnolo was pretty much the only thing a real cyclist with a real income would buy, I had to make do with the new kid on the block, Shimano’s ‘inferior’ but significantly cheaper parts. So I ended up with a bit of a rag bag of parts, mostly 600EX, one of Shimano’s early efforts at a racing group. Back in those days there weren’t any compatibility issues, no index shifting, so everything just worked with everything else. Easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By this time I had joined the local cycle club, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pnp.org.nz/club-and-history/club-historic-photos/&quot;&gt;Port-Nicholson-Poneke&lt;/a&gt;, or PNP as it is more commonly known. They had run the event at the track and they were the only club in Wellington proper, so there was no choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those of you used to dodging a litter of lycra-clad cool kids on carbon bikes on the weekend and (in London at least) waiting in queues of twenty or more bikes at the lights, let me set the scene for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was 1980 in a country that is rugby mad. The club, which covered the whole of the metropolitan Wellington area of 250,000 people had a membership of about 30. There were a couple of other clubs in the Wellington Region, two in the Hutt Valley and Kapiti-Mana, and then the club in the Wairarapa, Masterton. I’m guessing there were about 200 racers in the whole region. The only other people you would see on bikes back in those days were other racers and the ocassional weirdos with beards riding Dawes Galaxies, inevitably British expats (we’ll come back to those gents in about twelve bikes and thirty years time).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/5-pnp.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The Club. My mates Dan, Oli and Henry all in there. I am in there as Allen Taylor (long story).&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The club was run by ‘The Brays’ a family who lived out in Tawa and had the good grace to welcome legions of sweaty cyclists into their homes. Dave and Sandra ran the club and their two children, Fiona and Andy, were members. They even had a van with a sliding side door and a skylight - pretty flash back then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most sports clubs on the planet would probably operate in roughly the same way - a couple of extremely dedicated people at the core who did the boring stuff in order to give others the room to do what they loved, a ‘cool’ bit (in our club this was the Rice’s and Meo’s who never actually showed up to the club meetings or wore the club jerseys in races but got the best results) and then ‘the rest’ who formed the base of the club, bulking out the numbers and generally doing it for fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty quickly I fell in with a subset of the club, a few riders who gathered around the certifiably bike-mad Oli Brooke-White and ‘track stand champion’ Henry Chlebowicz. Oli and Henry worked as mechanics at The Bicycle Village and, due to it’s close location to my high-school, I defected from Burkes and took up residence there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After school, for as many days as the shop owner, Roland Hoffe (RIP), would tolerate, I would go down sit in the workshop and chat to ‘the boys’, looking at expensive parts as they came in, watching Oli and Henry at work and reading their expensive copies of the impossibly exotic International Cycle Sport - the only way we got any news cycling news from the continent.  These mags gave us iconic images of the cyclists of the era - Moser, Saronni, Fignon, Hinault and the occasional American like Le Mond. The idea that a kiwi would ever even be able to ride The Tour was really wild (I didn’t know that, in fact, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kennett.co.nz/product/harry-watson/&quot;&gt;that had already happened in 1928&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically we drooled over the magazines and did our best to copy the look of the bikes, clothes and, most importantly, the attitude of the European racers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;callout-left wide&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/5-oli.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Oli.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oli was the best at this by a long chalk. See photo evidence left where he does a terrific imitation of a Eurpoean pro at the end of a hard day. Oli will need no introduction to Wellington cyclists. A man of impeccable taste in bikes, generous and very very patient, he was then (and remains) a top wrench and a top bloke. He’s the kind of guy who would be a mechanic and confidante for British Cycling if he’d grown up here in the UK and not 12,000 miles away. Every club needs an Oli.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He has a nice blog, and I would recommend &lt;a href=&quot;http://oli-roadworks.blogspot.co.uk/2010/09/old-days-part-one.html&quot;&gt;his ‘old days’ series&lt;/a&gt; to you if you want some more pcis of 70s and 80s world cycling. He also has a &lt;a href=&quot;http://roadworksbicyclerepairs.tumblr.com&quot;&gt;nice tumblr blog of bike pics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back then he was a slender thing, riding impossibly large frames and making it look cool. He was the one with the bike that looked like it had just been purchased, every day, where my bike looked like I washed it once a year in cold water without soap. I still prefer riding bikes to looking after them and my mechanical skills are rudimentary - I have just enough to keep my bikes going and that’s it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;callout-left wide&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/5-shoes.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;We used to nail the cleats on...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point in the history of cycling they didn’t need a lot of looking after thankfully. All frames were steel, all racing bikes were ten speed with easy to look after friction shifting. Your chamois in your wool shorts was actually real goat leather, the soles of your Sidi’s were wood and you nailed your cleats to them. You had toe-straps and a single, small bottle on your bike. Lights were as effective as single candles. They were so dim the notion of a high and low was pointless. There were no HRMs, no power meters. I didn’t even have a speedo. I used to watch the milage in the car as we drove local roads to learn how long they were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My modern standards it was all very much seat of the pants. But I had the important things - I had my crew, I had some adults to organise races and point to at the start line, and I had a bike that was good enough. It didn’t make me sigh like Trevor Rice’s Benotto or the Rossin’s of the Meo brothers, but ‘The Gios’ did the job and I rode the fuck out of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also have no photos of it or me riding it, which is really weird considering how much of my life I had invested in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And my next bike? I have no photos of that either… but that may be just as well, considering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next: &lt;a href=&quot;/bikes/6-gios-rosa/&quot;&gt;Gios Rosa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2015 13:00:53 +1300</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/bikes/5-gios-negra/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/bikes/5-gios-negra/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>6. Gios Rosa</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I had a solid year racing the Gios. I won a couple of handicap races and was generally turning into a handy rider. I was what is known now as a ‘puncheur’ which is a polite way of saying that I couldn’t ride up hills. I am built L wide and M high, or ‘a bit hobbity’, and so the type of riding that favoured me was strength and sprint related. The short aggressive rides that the young riders did back then really suited me. Youth races never lasted much over an hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Criteriums were a favourite. These are circuit races on quiet roads usually flat and are ridden at top speed the whole way. In Wellington they were inevitably run around industrial estates, town centres on a Sunday morning and other generally abandoned bits of road. On longer, more hilly courses, I was quickly distanced on inclines, but could ride my way back to the other riders when we got to the flat easily enough. If I was in the front bunch as we got to the finish line I would come in somewhere in the top five most times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;callout-left wide&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/6-race.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Oli and Doug taking a corner at speed.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, the whole thing was done on instinct. The lack of coaching, lack of specialised knowledge and lack of measurement devices like speedos gave the whole thing a seat of the pants air. There was no comparing heart rates on forums, no development squads, no scholarships. The comparison was made on the road, in a race and the ultimate judge of fitness and form was your position over the line. In those days you used language not stats to describe your performance. The strange horse-racing like abstractions you hear out of racers mouths these days come from the pre-data logging era:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I had fresh legs today&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;I haven’t found my form yet&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;I was on the rivet&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last one of those refers to sitting well forward on a leather saddle to generate maxiumum power, a favourite of commentator and ex-pro Sean Kelly. &lt;em&gt;On the rivet&lt;/em&gt; is generally how I rode all the time. Racing wasn’t subtle, it was very hard, not helped by the fact that the road season was in the winter. In it’s infinite wisdom NZ Cycling placed the road season made this glorious decision, something to do with keeping the top riders (whoever they were) in sync with the European season. This meant that the rest of us raced and trained in the worst conditions imaginable. Combined with the gear - designed for a European summer - we were often soaked and freezing. A typical approach at the time to ‘winterising’ oneself was to buy a pair of large rugby socks, cut a hole where your cleats were, and wear them over your dainty Italian cycling shoes. In a Wellington winter that gave you ten minutes of pseudo-warmth before the wind and rain froze your feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All good character building stuff, but looking back on it I am a bit horrified. I remember riding along in pitch dark on A roads into howling gales and driving rain with lights that were less effective than a child’s torch, on a bike without mudguards, being sprayed with gritty water by passing cars. Soaked to the skin, the only thing that kept you from hypothermia was the heat produced from going as fast as you could. I must have had a huge amount of energy to burn, and a huge drive to push myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, this was just what you did. It’s what people who want to race still do. The clothing is so much better and the lights are fantastic but it’s still hard riding at night in heavy, inattentive, traffic with cold rain trickling down your neck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/6-rain.jpg&quot; height=&quot;288px&quot; /&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/6-rain2.jpg&quot; height=&quot;288px&quot; class=&quot;remove&quot; alt=&quot;http://lovelybike.blogspot.co.uk/&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Riding in the rain - something you just have to get used to on a bike.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lovelybike.blogspot.co.uk/&quot;&gt;2nd image via the very good lovelybike&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d moved jobs by this point. I’d given up the paper run and was working in ‘Manner’s Meats’, run by a shonky sexist arse called Pete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boy, was I naive. $22 a week to work from 4-6:30 every day, late on Fridays and Saturdays from 9 - 12 (most racing was Sunday).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were three guys who worked there. Pete, his henchman and an apprentice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They called me ‘Mork’ because they thought I was weird. Their definition of weird was this: Didn’t play rugby, didn’t call Maori ‘darkies’, didn’t talk about masturbation the whole time.  And let me tell you butchers talking about masturbation while holding knives, wearing white gumboots and hair nets, and cutting into flesh is an alarming sight. I suppose I was fascinated, I hadn’t spent any time close to people like this before, proper misogynst bigots - at least not as a perceptive teenager - and it’s clear to me now that spending time arund these guys was very help&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent most of my time out the back at a huge double sink, sluicing blood off trays, washing knives, wire-brushing the chopping blocks and listening to the radio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;960&quot; height=&quot;720&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/d5XJ2GiR6Bo?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;OMD Enola Gay. Listening to this washing blood and fat off trays - a life highlight.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also ran some deliveries (not on a bike sadly) got their food for them, mopped the floor and cleaned the display windows with vinegar-doused newsprint. Rememember my fabulous homelife? Most days when I finished I would go down to the Hungry Horse Burger bar, buy a hamburger (horseburger?) and sit and play ‘spacies’ for half an hour before then going out training in the dark, arriving home somewhere near eight or nine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;callout-left wide&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/6-spacies.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;I spent a lot of time on one of these - you could eat a greasy burger and play spacies &lt;i&gt;at the same time!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was 1981, the year of the infamous &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nzhistory.net.nz/culture/1981-springbok-tour&quot;&gt;Springbok tour of New Zealand&lt;/a&gt;. There were violent protests and a lot of civil disobedience. Everyone had an opinion and it really split the nation. There were two sides and the positions were clear - either you thought that apartheid was bad and NZ should be boycotting all sport with South Africa, or you through that ‘Sport and politics shouldn’t mix’. Basically the rugby lovers were on one side and the pinko-lefties were on the other. Members of families stopped talking to each other. My Mum sat on the motorway in protest - the rest of the family stopped talking to her for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/6-tour.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;81 Springbok Tour - healthy debate&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say the butchers were pro-tour. I, typically, was split down the middle. I could see both points of view. I remember a massive demo march in Wellington. Instead of joining it I rode behind it and around it on my bike. I didn’t participate so much as observe. It took me many many years to understand this tendency to stand back from events. I am something of a contradiction; I like to ‘fly’ and I like to think and create but I am not much of a joiner. The common thread is kinesthetics. I like to move and explore - whether that is in thought or motion I don’t really mind. Joining feels like being held inside a set of rules. Note that I am not a very good employee either!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point in life I was just beginning to see that I was a little different to many people I knew. I was ‘sensitive’, perhaps made more so by the dreadful home life, and I hated with a great passion the common mindset of kiwi male at that point. So if the common direction of the male was towards Rugby and being a good bloke and joining in for the good of all and respecting the spirit of ANZAC and all that other horse-shit I would set on a different path, just because. I would follow the individualist track and listen to music made with machines and have floppy hair and read European fiction and do this weird strange sport called cycling. And I would stay away, at all costs, from the All Blacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/6-saronni.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Saronni in the Maglia Rosa. My bike was exactly that colour.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what better way to do that than paint your bike pink?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so The Pink Gios was born. It actually was The Black Gios just repainted in Maglia Rosa pink. The colour of the leaders jersey in the Giro D’Italia, the cyclists real favourite tour - better than the Tour de France for those in the know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t have any stickers for it so it just became the pink bike. The butchers laughed, which is what I wanted of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not sure I would want a pink bike now, but considered in context it was about as radical and multiple piercings and tattoos. It was a romantic gesture in a very unromantic country,  new wave to your disco and cock-rock - and a very elegant, probably too-subtle, way of telling the butchers to fuck themselves. Cycling was - and still is - a very peculiar aesthetic. I can’t think of a sport that is so extremely difficult where men look so feminised. Skin tight lycra, shaved legs, dainty shoes, lots of colour. Maybe triathlons, where they add really short shorts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I left that job soon after. And soon after that, after a good two years of borrowship, Mouse called the loan of The Gios in. Fair enough. I’d had a good run with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure why, but I either couldn’t afford it or I didn’t think to offer, but I didn’t just buy the thing off Mouse. I stripped the parts off it and took it back in its extreme pinkness to Burke’s cycles - and was left with the immediate problem of being a racing cyclist without a bike to ride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next: &lt;a href=&quot;/bikes/7-the-divine-comedy/&quot;&gt;The Divine Comedy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2015 13:00:52 +1300</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/bikes/6-gios-rosa/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/bikes/6-gios-rosa/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>7. The Divine Comedy</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/7-finger.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;From the family photo album - Dan and I at a race. The bike of unknown make and model in all its tatty glory beside me. Note rust, mismatching forks, shocking handle bar tape. Taking the piss basically.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I picked The Unknown up in the paper, might have been a hundred bucks. It was sticker free, the owner had no idea what it was. It was steel and about the right size, that was all that mattered at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know why I didn’t petition my parents to buy me an actual decent racing bike - by this stage it would have been justified. I suspect I was becoming a bit arsey and contrary at this point - why be beholden in favours to my parents? Where would that get me? Nowhere. I was beginning to be obsessed with making my own way in the world - typical only-child divorced kid behaviour I guess. If that meant that the bike I would ride was the club joke, then so be it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Unknown was various colours, mostly a disgusting puce. The paint was old and chipped, the geometry a bit old-fashioned, so I suspect it was a racing bike from the late seventies. I immediately stripped all the parts off it, put all my stuff on it including _The Wheels_and started riding it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It kinda proved my point that the frame doesn’t matter that much as long as the wheels are good. My results stayed exactly the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually they got even better. I was sixteen now, I had served my apprenticeship and, as this was my final year as a ‘colt’ I was among the oldest and strongest in my age group. I was confusing statistic likelihoods with personal merit, but such ideas were way over my head at the time, I just liked being near the front most of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point I had managed to recruit my very good friend Dan into the cycling fold. Dan was a total natural on a bike and was beating me within a month of starting to ride properly. He was an excellent climber and had that useful body type - long and lean - that makes good athletes. We’ll meet Dan again in a few years time, at this time time he joined PNP and started riding races with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dan was part of a core of guys I hung out with at school. We were all in the same class and hung out together all the time. Dan, Greg, Danny, Peter… I imagine we were a bit exclusive, but we had a lot of fun. We weren’t geeky like the Dungeons and Dragons brigade (who, to be fair, were very bright and all went on to do interesting things in technology and science) but we were a witty bunch. The others had a real outdoor focus so I was always being dragged out on tramping trips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/7-tops.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;On a good day...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would go tramping in the Tararuas, carry in truck tire tubes and wetsuits and float out, that kind of thing, all without adult supervision, badges, levels or any of that kind of rubbish. It was terrific and, despite the occasional bad decision which thankfully cost no one their lives, we were safe. Having been toughened up on cycling the physical demands were easy. It was all completely analog - no phones, just maps and compasses and lots and lots of wool - lightweight gear was still a dream in someone’s head and the Tararuas were still the domain of possom hunters in Swandris. Tramping there is pretty simple - you are either on an exposed ridge, in a quiet, wet valley, or on a two-hour ascent or descent from one to the other. By benefit of not being a one of the featured NZ parks it is also dead quiet. I remember a five day walk Dan and I did once - we saw maybe four people. Magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/7-tongariro.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The tongariro crossing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dan and I even did the Tongariro crossing (with an ascent of Ngarahoe) in a day, running in our tramping boots - an early version of what gets called adventure racing these days. Gregg went on to create several adventure races. All good fun, and looking back I am amazed at how fit we were and how much activity we packed in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in the cycling world I would pick him up in Mum’s car (a fantastically ridiculous bright orange Datsun 120y) and we would drive out to a race. In those days you could get a full driving license with one test the day after you turned fifteen (cue a high level of rural road deaths).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/7-larking.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Mucking about post race.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing that Dan and I bought to our racing at this point was a good dose of teenage ‘awareness of absurdity’. That is we found quite a lot of suddenly very funny. &lt;em&gt;Everyone’s so effing serious&lt;/em&gt;. We would ride races together, and, at the same time, have a good laugh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somehow being on a rubbish bike made things even more fun. Riding in groups with expensive immaculate bikes while riding something that looked like it was put together in a couple of minutes and was clearly out of date was hugely entertaining. It was like racing against Ferraris in a battered old Escort and winning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why the comedy was divine - we could laugh, give the flash guys the finger and win  - all at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/7-sprint.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Doug winning the seniors sprint, in the backgroound the 'Braymobile' of club stalwarts, The Brays, with Oil cheering on to the right.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was on this bike that I won my only two medals. Half way through the season the region had a round of races where riders from clubs that didn’t normally race together could compare themselves before the end of year regional championships - they were called the ‘Halfway-Centres’. That year it was held in the Nelson area, so after a quick flight in the morning we had a ten mile time trial in the afternoon. I can’t remember the time I did, but I remember a fast tail-wind out and a furious stomp into a bad headwind on the way back, so the time wouldn’t have been great. But I did get second, which surprised me. Antosh (see below) was first from memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day I somehow read the race perfectly, timed my sprint just right, and won it by a matter of inches from a guy called Darien Rush. His Linkedin profile says: ‘Former NZ &amp;amp; Oceania Elite Road Cycling Champion, Olympic &amp;amp; Commonwealth Games Squad Member’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the course had been two feet longer he would have won it, but I wasn’t complaining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So - two medals, silver and gold, both on a the anti-snob bike, a bike that shamed everything around it and absorbed light. Being naturally skeptical of my own abilities I would say I was lucky but then you don’t do well in a time trial by luck. I must have been right on form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course it’s nice to win, but the problem with that is that people start to want you to take things seriously. And this was not a time of my life to start doing that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, not sport at least. As I have said somewhere above kiwis take their sports, even their obscure sports like cycling, very seriously. I didn’t quite know it yet but that laugh I was sharing with Dan would soon turn into a full-on anti-sport rebellion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/7-classics.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Penguin classics, $1 a go.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was sixteen and suddenly aware there was a world beyond Miramar and Wellington High School. How did I know about it? The newspapers were no good and magazines took three months on a boat to reach us and were too expensive to actually buy. So I got to know a version of the outside world through… novels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friends with older siblings started passing round the kind of books that a group of clever arsey boys might like - Catch 22, World According to Garp, that kind of stuff. I loved this style of American writing, the pure energy, the language jumping off the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But left to my own devices I read Euro fiction: cool, intense writing from Hesse, Grass, Mann, Camus. I’d been visiting Silvio’s bookshop on Cuba St where you could buy a tatty, discarded novel from the Penguin modern classic series for a dollar a throw. I stacked them up by my bed and retreated there in the evening, and read late into the night, avoiding my curdling father downstairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What have cheap paperbacks got to do with cycling? Nothing. And that was the point. Up to this stage in my life I had wanted to be that thing that seemed obvious that a clever kid should be - a scientist. I had a bent for Astronomy and even at twelve I was going to lectures up at the Carter Observatory on it. I think there was the boys natural curiosity there - where am I in the universe? But also there were decent, big ideas in Astronomy. Black holes. Concepts that made your head bigger on the inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was beginning to need that. &lt;em&gt;Something more.&lt;/em&gt; I was beginning to notice art and girls and clothes and girls and how my hair was cut and girls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cycling was not a cultural phenomenon in its own right back then. There was none of the hipster cultism, the MAMIL networking, the post-ride espresso culture. It was just riding a bike, as fast as you possibly could until the finish line meant the hurt could stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was an above average rider, but I was never going to be great. How do I know this? Well let me introduce to the real thing, a guy called Antosh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/7-antosh.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;What Antosh looks like now, in his 40s. I am amazed I ever kept up with him.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antosh was a cousin of Henry’s and he was a total natural. Absolutely gifted. He was naturally lean but somewhere in there was an engine and a resolve that never gave up. I remember him leaping off the front in a race up the coast and getting 50 metres on four or five of us. Four or five riders is about the perfect size group for pulling in a lone rider - it should take anywhere between one minute and five to pull back 50 metres. We got him back to 5 metres, and then the others kinda assumed he would give up and slip back to us, which would have been the sensible thing to do, to conserve his energy. Nope, he just kept going. I remember rallying the others to go again and then winching him back, seemingly a centimetre at a time, until finally he was back in the fold. If you gave him an inch he would take a hundred yards and keep it until the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was what talent looked like. He had what the top riders have, a brutalising strength coupled with a deep but very well controlled aggression. He probably didn’t realise that he had the ace up his sleeve though - a mind that was an ally. If you have a mind that is more than usually prone to bad thoughts, feeling of self-doubt and the like you are going to find it harder to push yourself physically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antosh is still a pretty awesome cyclist, and although club supremo Alan Rice always said he could take it to the top if he wanted he must have never wanted enough. He lives in Melbourne and runs a &lt;a href=&quot;http://cognitivecycling.com/home.html&quot;&gt;bikefit business&lt;/a&gt;, and for many years he was a regular local face, wrenching bikes in Wellington shops, decimating training rides and dominating local races.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/7-punch.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The great Bernard Hinault showing his aggressive side on a french protestor - not the picture of left-wing tolerance...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People who are good at sports have a blend of ambition, aggression, the right genes, kinaesthetic talent and the ability to treat training as a serious pursuit. The good ones study training, they set goals, train for them, analyse. I am guilty of being someone who just rides my bike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is I was not - nor am I now - mentally suited to enduring pain. That is to say I find it difficult to put my mind &lt;em&gt;outside&lt;/em&gt; the pain. I am too neurotic, not steady enough, too flaky, hot and cold. Good athletes find a way of shutting out or moving outside of pain, and that requires mental toughness, a single mindedness, that was beyond me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there I was, being confronted with my own physical limits by the superior Antosh, having my mind blown up in a series of terrific books, and was beginning to see sport as a contradictory thing, sometimes humorous and divine but more often than not a paradoxically pointless waste of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These things were not pointing to a career at the highest end of cycling! Not that I had ever deluded myself into thinking I was going to win the Tour de France - and maybe that was the marker; if I had dreamed about winning the Tour de France then that ambition might have taken me somewhere. As it was I had stumbled onto a moment of success as indicated by two pieces of rapidly tarnishing metal - one silverish, the other one a bit goldy. Did I know it would be the highlight of my sporting life at the time? Nope. Am I still just a little bit proud of winning that day? Yep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with my two medals freshly won, my cycling club no doubt a bit humiliated by the state of my bicycle, decided to do something about it and they chose to help me out by being the first recipient of the club Alan. Or, as we knew it, the dead man’s bike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next: &lt;a href=&quot;/bikes/suffering/&quot;&gt;Interlude: On Suffering&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2015 13:00:50 +1300</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/bikes/7-the-divine-comedy/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/bikes/7-the-divine-comedy/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Interlude - Suffering</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a word you will hear all the time in cycling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suffering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sports people, being a body-led, kinaesthetic bunch, are often not the world’s best describers, so a few words get used time and time again and become rammed with meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;I made them suffer&lt;/b&gt; - to up the tempo on a climb&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;I was suffering&lt;/b&gt; - other riders were putting me on the ropes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;You have to know how to suffer&lt;/b&gt; - describing the willingness to put yourself in the hurt locker in order to win&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Suffering for my sport&lt;/b&gt; - as in the life style you have to live&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Suffering&lt;/b&gt; - as a way to describe the desperate pain of trying to go faster&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Suffering&lt;/b&gt; - a way of describing the nobility of cycling&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Suffering&lt;/b&gt; - a way of describing the quasi-mystical element of enduring pain in the pursuit of excellence&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Suffering&lt;/b&gt; - the cost of having &lt;em&gt;The Passion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;Suffering is our unit of measure, our currency, and yes, our virtue. It is also the single most difficult thing to explain to the non-cyclist.&quot;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.velominati.com/guest-article/guest-article-on-suffering/&quot;&gt;@Csos on Velominati&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dictionary gives two meanings of the word; &lt;em&gt;being subjected to something unpleasant&lt;/em&gt; and the archaic &lt;em&gt;to undergo martyrdom or execution&lt;/em&gt;. In cycling it can mean both at the same time; it can describe the pain of the sport, from the way you are riding on the day to the gritty ouch of a road rash, and it can describe the metaphysical yearning behind the cyclist’s task, an understanding of the extreme agony of existence. Suffering will lead to redemption - on the good days at least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/a2-chris.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Photos of Chris Hoy training.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the simple things like discomfort and physical pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bike racing, like any sport where you are committed to push yourself on a regular basis, is really hard. You force your body into applications of effort that are both uncomfortable and, given how life works these days, totally unneccessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How hard is hard? I know when I’ve really pushed myself when, as soon as I finish a ride, I have to lie down and wait for ten minutes for the nausea to go away. That’s very common at all levels of the sport, everyone has to do it (see photos of Chris Hoy above). Some get that feeling worse than others - I remember a cyclist I used to race against who would regularly have a little throw up after crossing the line. Nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pros got a lot further. Tommy Simpson famously pushed himself into an early grave  climbing Mt Ventoux (not helped by amphetimines). Riders are regularly scooped up by team assistants on the finish line, totally spent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/a2-fabian.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;A day at the office for Fabian Cancellara.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even at the local amateur level racing is very demanding. Putting yourself in that much pain regularly is just not something many people want to do.  The whole sportive thing is probably great - I don’t do them - but when riders try their first short circuit race the shift in intensity really catches them out. In an hour-long circuit race the pace is on from the start, you don’t get a chance to warm into it, your heart rate is maxing out in a minute and it stays there, the whole way. You don’t manage yourself into and out of pain, you are just shifting the pain level from &lt;em&gt;just about endurable&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;this really fucking hurts.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the things that haven’t changed about cycling since it began. You can add all the tech you want on top of it, but the fundamental experience is that of suffering to go faster. The bikes have changed, but the look on the racers faces hasn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t fake it. Even when the cheat and sociopath Lance Armstrong was riding up those hills EPO’ed off his face he was still, undeniably, in the depths of suffering. The drugs made him faster, but they didn’t make it hurt less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my mind this is why racing cyclists are so particular about how they look - it’s a kind of armour. And it even explains why proper roadies are often just so bloody rude to ordinary cyclists. The agony a pro embraces is many orders of magnitude greater than even a good amateur cyclist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love the somewhat overwrought description of training by kiwi lead-out supremo Greg Henderson:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“Training is like fighting a gorilla. You don’t stop when you’re tired; you stop when the gorilla’s tired.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well that’s as it should be if you want to make it to the top. If you want to be a pro. Or even a good amateur. And the daily question the racer has to ask themselves is - how much am I prepared to suffer? And then they have to go out and do it. You don’t prove it by planning it or writing about it, you have to ‘put blood on the road’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hate to leave the last word on basic physical pain to Armstrong, but he describes this &lt;em&gt;wanting&lt;/em&gt; pain well:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Cycling is so hard, the suffering is so intense, that it’s absolutely cleansing. The pain is so deep and strong that a curtain descends over your brain…. Once, someone asked me what pleasure I took in riding for so long. “Pleasure?” I said. “I don’t understand the question. I didn’t do it for the pleasure; I did it for the pain.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why would you want pain? I am going to come back to this later - in about fifteen bikes time - when I start to get interested in endurance. For the moment let’s just note that pain is a fantastically useful feedback system. It lets you know what is happening in your body. Without it riding a mile, or hunting game on the Savannah, would be impossible. There’s a reason people say that you need to build your &lt;em&gt;ability to suffer&lt;/em&gt;. You need to be able to suffer to progress beyond riding to the pub and back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/a2-saronni.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Suffering and causing suffering - Saronni.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The common understanding of road racing is that you ‘suffer faster’ to paraphrase American rider Greg Lemond. But it’s not just this, it’s not just that racing cyclists suffer - all cyclist’s have the discomfort of pushing themselves. What sets racing cyclists apart is that they have to want to inflict that suffering on other people. Sure, they are not punching their opponents in the face, but made no mistake, the aim is to annihilate them, to attack, to ‘drop’ them - to make them suffer in order to vanquish them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why there are so many great photos of two riders riding side by side up the climbs in the grand tours. They are trying to match each other, to gauge the form of their great enemy, in order to break them into little pieces. This is what getting ‘the look’ from Armstrong meant - &lt;em&gt;I am going to kill you.&lt;/em&gt; A good sport for a sociopath then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/a2-pantani-armstrong.jpg&quot; height=&quot;280px&quot; /&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/a2-hinault-fignon.jpg&quot; height=&quot;280px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/a2-coppi.jpg&quot; height=&quot;280px&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Head to head over the decades: Armstrong and Pantani; Hinault and Fignon; Coppi and Bartali&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what’s the compensation for this physical suffering and aggression, why would you bother?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being really top-notch fit is amazing. It’s about speed of course but also efficiency. You are in tune with the bike - bent to it really - and while this should feel like you are owned by the bike it reverses and it feels wonderful. You have a sense of mastery. You know exactly how fast you can go and for how long and you time your efforts perfectly. You can push deeper into the suffering knowing that your body will not only recover it will feel even stronger afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s Cadel Evans on winning the 2009 World Road Champs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

In Mendrisio I felt it - the exhilaration of what the bike has to offer. It's a simple machine that conjures a vast mix of emotions. It can evoke the senses and raise the spirits of people who watch. For those who ride it can seem like the perfect vehicle for transport. For those who race, there's no better sensation than being on top of your gear making mountains feel like flat roads. Cycling throws up plenty of obstacles, unknown territory, high speed split-second considerations. Where to next? What's around the next corner? Who cares? You're flyin'!&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the feeling - any anyone can have it, if they train hard enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not withstanding the fact that professional cyclists tend to die early (!) the regular riding of a bicycle makes you not only fit but also mostly healthy. Endurance sport is good for you full stop. Sure you have to look after your posture and flexibility but the thinking is that you have a heart that runs about ten years younger than the general population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember chatting with a guy who had done Paris-Brest-Paris (a 1200km 90 hour ride) six times. He thought that long-distance cycling changed you at a cellular level - for the better I should add. He looked amazing and emitted a warm glow, as if he was fired from inside by a small bunsen burner of vigour. The last time I saw him was overtaking me on a hill out of Carhaix on the 2015 Paris-Brest-Paris at around 3am on night two. He is over seventy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also something great about getting outside. I love a good windy commute and sometimes a storm is a great experience. You are in it, not watching, not hiding. You are in the world and the world is in you. I am a city-dwelling web-guy so much of my life is regulated, and in the grand scheme of things having a headwind on a commute for 30 minutes is hardly a wilderness experience, but in London it helps keep me sane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally racing is fun. It’s very strategic, there’s a lot of bluffing, but mostly it is kinetically exhilarating. Being in the middle of a group of riders charging along at 25-30mph is a buzz in it’s own right. It’s a very intense experience. You have to be right on the ball, all the time. Double that on the track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see some of this these days with the new cameras - the closeness of the other riders, the jostling for position, the shouting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing this video doesn’t capture is the amount of snot that flies around!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/QE97iUvSHk0?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enough about simple suffering. Let’s get metaphysical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The buddists are all over this. Dukkha (suffering) is the first noble truth:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Birth is suffering, aging is suffering, illness is suffering, death is suffering; union with what is displeasing is suffering; separation from what is pleasing is suffering; not to get what one wants is suffering.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a brutal place to start a religion from, but luckily the Buddha spent a lot of time on empathy and kindness to compensate. Which is a good thing for a religion, but no so relevant for a sport. Buddism revolves around the notion that you would want to escape suffering, but racing cyclists turn the other way, ride into it and are generally not too worried about compassion when they close on the finishing line at 40mph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the great Fausto Coppi said simply that &lt;em&gt;cycling is suffering&lt;/em&gt;. I suspect he was not conscious that he was paraphrasing the buhhda, and he was certainly not telling anyone to avoid the suffering, he was just stating a fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cycling in all its forms is very much a product of Western mindset and Western industrialised society, and I think it’s a sport that is best thought of in terms of the official religion of that society. I am not talking about the scientific method, I am talking about the Christian tradition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my mind there is something of a protestant hangover in the toil of the British cyclist grinding out a big gear along an A road at 8 o’clock on a cold Sunday morning in the ‘Club 25’. And a more catholic version saturates the warmer southern climes of Europe and South American where cyclists are followed like saints and are expected to suffer as much - their small silver crosses bobbing on their pigeon chests as they climb and climb and climb up the worlds steepest and highest passes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The intersecting area of the Venn diagram of religion and cycling meets its apogee in the small church, the Madonna del Ghisallo, AKA The Cyclists Church (blessed by Pope Pius XII in 1949) above Lake Como, where frames and jerseys hang as icons. In typical Catholic fashion there is even the macabre, the very bicycle that local cyclist Fabio Casartelli was riding when he fell off the Col de Portet d’Aspet in 1995 and died. A genuine relic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/a2-church.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Interior of the Madonna del Ghisallo&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this view of cycling to suffer is to is to be made honest by being stripped back to the bone and so approach the divine. To make a sacrifice in order to overcome the mundane and touch the cycling shoe of God. You can see this in the Tour de France on the big mountain days. Riders that have been hiding in the peloton have to come to the front and endure hours of intense pain in order to prove that they are worthy to take on the cloak of the Yellow Jersey - the holy shroud of cycling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The great riders become images of suffering for glory. Anquetil, Coppi, Merckx, Hinault. Iconic. Like religious figures their faces are etched with pain. They burn themselves to mark themselves worthy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suffering on the bike even looks a lot like the suffering of the saints. There are many photos to choose from when you want to illustrate this - here are a sprinkling, &lt;a href=&quot;https://uk.pinterest.com/philipatlitton/road-bike-suffering/&quot;&gt;there’s many more&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/a2-suffer.jpg&quot; height=&quot;280px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/a2-m.jpg&quot; height=&quot;280px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/a2-kelly2.jpg&quot; height=&quot;280px&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;(l-r) &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.russellis.co.uk/national-hill-climb&quot;&gt;An amateur from last years UK hill climb time trial - a highly recommended gallery&lt;/a&gt; - Merckx, Kelly.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyclists at this level of the game become stars. They exist outside of the mortal firmament and ascend to the heavens. Immortalised in stories, occassionally covered in money, they become secular saints. Many cyclists resist this (Bradley Wiggins is a good example), others embrace and amplify their deity (Armstrong) and sometimes they fall a long, long way back to earth, often with a sickening thud (Armstrong, but equally many cyclists from that era - Pantani, Landis, Hamilton, Ulrich, Basso).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are used to the massive media profile of cyclists these days, specially here in the UK since cycling  started to take itself seriously and get some money behind it. But cyclists have long been adored, between the two wars and into the ninetines cycling in Europe was pretty much confined to Europeans, but before the First World War cycling was more global and created stars as big, if not bigger, than they are today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crowds at Madison Square Gardens regularly topped 10,000. When English pro cyclist Bert ‘Invincible’ Harris hit his head on the track and died in 1897 &lt;em&gt;tens of thousands&lt;/em&gt; of mourners turned up on the streets to Leicester to mourn his passing. Then there’s the amazing story of Major Taylor, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.smithsonianmag.com/history/the-unknown-story-of-the-black-cyclone-the-cycling-champion-who-broke-the-color-barrier-33465698/?no-ist=&quot;&gt;the first black sports star&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;callout-left wide&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/a2-taylor.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Major Taylor&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sports star is not exclusive to the bike, but the origin of the modern professional athlete is very much the story of the professional cyclist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we can say that the church of capitalism is the ruling religion of the modern world, then we can surely say that sports personalities, through their ‘miraculaous’ performances, are regularly beatified by the media as secular saints. Where once religion was the opium of the masses, now professional sport is the religion of the consumer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with all religion there is plenty of room for corruption in the church of sport and the congregation of cyclists that turn up weekly in their lycra rainment, sipping the magical water of electrolyte drink. The forms of corruption range from the drugs (from opium and burgundy to speed balls and EPO), to race fixing, bribery, bullying. There is even &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/greglemond/posts/10151127372613494&quot;&gt;the corrupt pope&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://road.cc/content/news/187733-british-cycling-suspends-shane-sutton-over-sexism-claims&quot;&gt;plenty of people who think they are beyond reproach.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will come back to the religious festival that is the Tour de France and the ‘green’ credentials of professional cycling (hint - there have none) when I explore capitalism and cycling in more detail in a later aside, but for me it encapsualtes the extremes of suffering very well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a basic level the grand tours (France, Italy, Spain) are three weeks of physical intensity it is impossible to imagine. A few hundred riders endure the pain of riding, the living out of a suitcase, and intense media scrutiny. Then there’s the fact that any one of the 2.3 million people that line the route could topple you with a misplaced placard or camera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/a2-stress.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Hurt.&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The suffering is physical and, unlike the shorter events, the mental drain is huge. Helicopters over you all the time, the moto riders shoving a camera in your face as you grimace up a mountain, the pictures broadcast live to the world, the manager giving you orders through the radio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there are the elected stages where the race can actually be won. Here those who want to be ‘the one’ must come forward and flay themselves in public as commentators pick out their weaknesses. To slow down has a moral dimension. You haven’t worked hard enough, you are not trying hard enough. The truth is that the individuals who would hope to be King or Queen are almost identically well trained and motivated, what the race comes down to is the strength of your team and your genetic heritage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yet we watch it again and again for the stars battling each other, for pulling out career defining performances, for their feats of suffering. It creates its own glory and, for all that The Tour is a money machine, it is also a platform for great individuals and their teams to entertain us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the one who is gifted and suffers the most the glory is endless. The worldly spoils are relatively modest by sporting standards, but they join an exclusive order of the greats. Their suffering has bought you to a state of grace, from here you need never turn a pedal ever again, nor do they have anything to prove to anyone. They transubtansiate into an eternal presence of a brand and the faithful mimic them on the weekends, cranking up Box Hill or out along one of the world’s countless time trial courses, each one of them pushing that little bit harder remembering what the great one did on Ventoux, or the Alp d’Huez. The legions rise in their name, literally ascending the site of pilgrimage, high-tech versions of the old penitents who found grace by crawling their way to the sites of holiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What perhaps is strangest of all is that these same cyclists - having won something really big like the Tour de France, or a track world championship or even an elite national championship - don’t just hang up their wheels. No, they keep putting themselves through travails to try and win things again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/a2-passion.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Pantani, full of EPO, in full pomp&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason why is the final shared secret of all cyclists, what makes them the faithful. We all know the suffering but there is something else, that thing that overtakes you, that means you have to watch yourself at dinner parties lest you start raving about your next big ride, that makes you think that having another bike cluttering up the house is a logical choice, that has you gazing at maps and building bicycles in your mind. This is the thing that keeps the pros coming back to the insanity of racing year after year, this thing keeps you motivated and on your bike in the deepest, coldest winter and makes you take holidays filled with hills and rain and joyfully tolerate getting older and slower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s a topic to leave for another day:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Passion&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next: &lt;a href=&quot;/bikes/8-dead-mans-bike/&quot;&gt;Dead Man’s bike - The ALAN&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2015 13:00:50 +1300</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/bikes/suffering/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/bikes/suffering/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>8. Dead Man's Bike</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/8-title.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Andrew Meo (red cap, blue jacket), David Meo (yellow cap), David Barnett (white cap, red/white jacket), Allan Tindale (pale blue cap and jacket), Mike Podmore (white cap, yellow jacket), Trevor Rice (black cap, behind David Barnett), Richard Walters (red cap, at the back). &lt;a href=&quot;https://lagazzettadellabici.wordpress.com/2010/03/04/riding-through-glenside-everyday-cycling-heros/&quot;&gt;From this blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of how the club had a frame it could lend to a promising youngster like me is not a happy one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t know Mike Podmore that well, he was a couple of years older than me and, even though we had a common friend in Oli, Mike did the kind of training that us ‘colts’ didn’t need - long miles. He would regularly knock off the ‘Akas’ ride - a 100 mile loop through the lovely Akatarawa ranges. I was happier at 10 miles absolutely flat-out, 100 would have bored me to tears at that stage of my life - a weekly 50 was plenty for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me leave &lt;a href=&quot;http://oli-roadworks.blogspot.co.uk/2009/06/training-with-conviction.html&quot;&gt;the telling of the story to Oli&lt;/a&gt;, off his blog:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Mike was a lad from Island Bay with a single-minded determination to succeed in his sport, with a view to eventually heading to Belgium to try his fortunes on the big Euro stage. I accompanied him on many training rides as he trained hard towards this goal, and as he prepared to race the gruelling Dulux Tour of the North Island. Along with other good race performances over the year a gutsy performance as eventual Lanterne Rouge in the 1982 Dulux (won that year by Stephen Carton) convinced him he had what it took once he’d put in “more moiles, Oli, more moiles…” so off we rode around and around the Akas until I was in the form of my life and/or completely broken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Eventually it came time to farewell Poddy as he flew off to meet his destiny. Sadly, that destiny proved to be a cruel one. He was killed during his first pedal strokes on Belgian soil, while riding to meet up with his new club. In the middle of the afternoon he was hit head on by a drunk driver crossing over into the wrong side of the road, killing Mike instantly. His death hit the Wellington cycling community very hard and he was sorely missed for his Muttley snicker and great good humour.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being killed as you left the airport to pursue a dream - how brutal is that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;callout-left wide&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/8-poster.jpg&quot; height=&quot;350px&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Early Dulux Tour Poster&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oli’s sidelong reference to his ‘lantern rouge’ performance in the Dulux Tour of New Zealand shows that Mike had the stamina, but also kinda proves the adage that you get better at the kind of riding that you do. Seems obvious, but if the kind of riding you do is long slow distance and you never put in speed work then you are going to finish the race, but you are most likely to be last.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A season racing in Belgium would have fixed that for Mike. An acquaintance of mine who tried racing there many years later said it was blisteringly fast and that you only needed one gear - the biggest one you had. And this was a man who competed in the kilo time-trial at international level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m ashamed to say it but Mike’s death didn’t really register with me at the time. Death seems like a distant and odd thing to a sixteen year old. Now, being a parent, I can’t imagine anything worse. Losing a son in the prime of his life would be an endless hell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somehow his parents found a place of generosity inside their grief and the gave Mike’s old kit to the club. This included an ALAN, rather conveniently in my size. Spurred on by the embarrassment of having me ride around on an utter piece of crap, the club decided I would be the first recipient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/8-alan-sr.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;An ALAN of roughly the same era&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alanbike.it/&quot;&gt;ALAN&lt;/a&gt; were an innovative Italian cycling company who not only produced the first aluminium racing cycle (1972) but also the first carbon racing frame (1976). Depending on who you believe ALAN stands for ALuminium ANodised, or it’s an amalgam of the owner’s first children’s names - ALberto and ANnamaria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an age of steel bikes ALANs looked utterly gorgeous, like polished jewels. Now days we like our bikes stealthy and back in the eighties it was all about the glossy paint job on your steel bike, so the anodised shine of the the ALAN was distinct. Being made of aluminium they were a good pound lighter than a steel frame - very important for the club ‘lift-test’ at the beginning of club runs. They were constructed by using threaded aluminium tubes that were ‘screwed and glued’ into place using techniques borrowed from the aeronautical industry. It’s a method of manufacture that seems quaint in an age of 3d printing and carbon moulding, but at the time it was radical. A bike frame that was glued together? Next you’ll be telling me they can be made out of plastic!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/8-build.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Aviation and architectural influences&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However there was one serious drawback. Without going into the theory of metalullurgy you will have to trust me when I say that an alloy tube of a similar diameter wall-thickness to a steel tube is going to be more flexible. Even by using thickened tubes as ALAN did the frames still felt quite ‘soft’. There was so much deflection in the seat tube I could quite comfortably get the chain grinding on the front derailleur while riding up hill sitting down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It probably wasn’t the best frame for a burly lad like myself, but the springy nature of the construction method never stopped Sean Kelly winning tons of races on his Vitus 979 (a french bike built on the same idea).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I swapped out all my parts onto the new frame (exactly the same parts, third frame) and had a shiny new bike. This happened a month or so after my medal-winning spree at the ‘halfway’ champs. I should have been set up nicely for the Centre champs, and then possibly the nationals. There were much stronger riders in the region (Antosh and Darien and Dan for example) but I might have edged into a team at fourth or fifth spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But by now I just didn’t care. As the races kept going by I was rapidly losing interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/8-allen.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Me, behind, looking tired. Note &lt;s&gt;helmet&lt;/s&gt; collection of vinyl straps.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the only photo I have of me racing a bike in that final year. It’s a terrible shot. You can’t see the bike and it doesn’t even look like me. I remember the race, it was a criterium around Kent and Cambridge terrace - my kind of race, short, flat and very fast. I finished third or fourth, Darien won it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Darien won it both because he really wanted to win it. He was gunning for regional selection - which he got and he went on to do very well for himself as a cyclist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t want to win and when you don’t want to win what’s the point in racing? I’d had enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a crazy few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know when people say they changed over night for apparent reason and you think ‘nah, people don’t change that much’. Well I changed out of recognition. I’m not sure if these things were always in me looking for a way out - I guess my parents would know that - but from the inside it felt like life took a large and unexpected right turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to this I had wanted to be a scientist. I was good at math and geography. I took economics and physics rather than art history and french. Then something strange happened. I took a series of after-school drama classes run by a Theatre in education group called ‘The Town and Country Players’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was like someone had thrown a switch. I simply stepped out of one life and into another and remained there for ten fun, chaotic, stressful and very poor years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had always had a performative streak, but in those days that kind of thing was generally considered to be ‘showing off’ and I had even been told at primary school that &lt;em&gt;I needed to get it out of my system&lt;/em&gt;. And fuck you too Mrs Martin. But here were a bunch of feisty misfits and gloriously artistic oddballs swanning around doing trust exercises, wearing dungarees and having a ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hold on. This was not about suffering. This was about, you know, being happy and joyful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To say that I forgot about cycling is an understatement. I dropped it from my life in an instant and didn’t even notice it was gone. Cycling seemed one-dimensional in comparison, a shadow of a real experience. In theatre you connect with people - it is the basic proposition. In cycle racing the aim is to separate yourself from the crowd - that’s what winning is. &lt;em&gt;I was stronger. I was better. I am different.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d had enough of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started going to the Public library after school and listening to records at the listening booths six at a time, randomly sampling everything from Bach to American minimalism to free jazz to punk. Upstairs, in the beautiful New Zealand room, under the scowling regard of the librarian there I started to read the back catalogue of Kiwi poets and novelists and discover that New Zealand has amazing artists and writers. It was also occurring to me for the first time that New Zealand was culturally distinct. It was it’s own force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/8-colin.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there in the New Zealand room, in amongst the art books and monographs, I started to discover the rich alternative seam of ‘not kiwi males’, those who had forged an identity based on art; the Sargensons and McCahons and Baxters and Curnows. Those were the big names at the time, but there were plenty more and I started to recognise them as ‘my men’. Men who were happy to push beneath the surface, look at the myths and ask questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I gave up &lt;em&gt;tough&lt;/em&gt; and took up &lt;em&gt;flexible&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;expressive&lt;/em&gt; instead. I started writing a journal. I started writing writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was the bomb that was going off in me - culture - and in the theatre I got to take part in it. I had found a place where you were allowed to be happy and sad and difficult and provocative and arty. Where you could be all of your selves at once. This was particularly useful for someone like me who was at the time (and remain perpetually) a bit shattered. The easy thing to say here is that multiple divorces and step-fathers and all that are not a great recipe for settled personalities but I would also have to say that I am by temperament and most likely genetic lottery a person without solid borders. I seem to feel things more acutely than most others, for better and worse. The ‘artistic temperament’ I guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back on it I can see that cycling had been an important part of my transition out of a suburban mindset.
We were culturally isolated for sure, but cycling was a first bridge to an wider culture. There were connections between reading Camus and knowing what a peloton was, between learning about futurism and riding an Italian racing bike and knowing that Kraftwerk were absolute bike nuts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;960&quot; height=&quot;720&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/sQz-CZvkY8k?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not going to be going on about theatre in this series - this is meant to be about bikes after all - but there is a shift in emphasis I need to put to you here. From this point on I have only ever entered three races in 30 years, so if you are into road racing and the suffering and the glory well maybe you should go and read Froome’s autobiography. If you are interested in what place a bicycle can have in a life that is also about many other things, then please stay with me because there is plenty of that to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have written about eight bikes so far. There’s around 25 still to do. They range from utter pieces of crap bought to save money on bus fares through to full-suspension mountain bikes through to Titanium tourers, carbon road bikes and steel fixies. We’ve got a lot of commuting to do, tons of mountain biking, a stint as a cycle courier, some touring and then, finally, a heap of Audax (long-distance road-riding). We’ve even got a bit of trials to do and some riding in skateboard bowls. My cycling history is nothing if not varied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve also got two new countries to live in, a good few ‘careers’, bouts of depression and anxiety to cope with, strange diets, many years of the glorious stupidity of youth, a bit of maturing to do and a lot of cycles I could never afford to buy to obsess over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the ALAN? Someone noticed that I wasn’t turning up for races and wanted the thing back. Fair enough. So suddenly I didn’t have a bike, instead I had a box of those same components I had used to put together the Pink Gios a few years previous. They probably ended up in a parts bin or on a mate’s training bike somewhere, I can’t remember now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw an ALAN in the street just the other day, chained to a pole. Of course since the hipsters ‘discovered’ 80s bikes it’s nothing to see a bearded man riding a Rossin or Guercotti road frame with the stupid narrow bars on, but here was an ALAN with a old Campagnolo groupset and Cinelli drop bars on it. It could have been the very bike that I last rode in 1984.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the same day I was beginning to write this post - chance surely? I stood for a while gazing at it, the smokers nearby looking at me like I was mad. Still a lovely thing to look at, a proper jewel of a bike, one where the frame itself captures the spirit of engineering excellence and elegance that all bikes are but few really show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I certainly didn’t appreciate the bike enough at the time I had it - I didn’t know it would be the nicest bike I would own for decades - nor did feel the loss of Mike nearly enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, a very belated thank you to my Club and Mike’s parents now, and a quick silent prayer (what else to call it?) for Mike as I stand on the site of busy London street near enough to 35 years later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And with that we will leave road racing behind, and take up the bicycle in a myriad of other forms. I hope you want to continue on the journey with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next: &lt;a href=&quot;/bikes/9-girls-bike-dandy/&quot;&gt;Girl’s bike dandy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2015 13:00:49 +1300</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/bikes/8-dead-mans-bike/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/bikes/8-dead-mans-bike/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
